{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This artist may depict Harman van Swole in a Portrait of a Slav Prince later bought by Catherine the Great. This artist was hired by the Guild ofSurgeonsinhishomenationto paint the dissection ofthedeceasedcriminalArisKindt.Anotherworkbythismandepictsa shooting company led by FranzBanningCocq[[\"COKE\"]]inTheNightWatch.Fortenpoints, name this prolific Dutch artist whose other work includes many self-portraits and The Anatomy Lesson of Dr. Nicolaes Tulp. ANSWER:Rembrandtvan Rijn(orRembrandtHarmenszoonvan Rijn; accept either underlined portion) (2) Medal of Honor-winner Bud Day saved this man'slifeafterhedroppedathirdofhis body weight while in the Vietnamese POW camp called \"The Plantation.\" With Russ Feingold, this senator names a campaign reform bill which limits the amount of \"soft money\" available to candidates. This politician succeeded Barry Goldwater as senatorfrom Arizona in 1987. The 2008 Republican candidateforU.S.presidentwas,fortenpoints,what politician who died in 2018?",
      "answer": "JohnMcCainor John SidneyMcCainIII"
    },
    {
      "question": "Callimachus [[kah-lee-MAH-kuss]] died atthisbattlewhilechasingthelosingsideto their ships. One side in this battle failed to get reinforcements due to the Carneia [[kar-NAY-uh]] festival. The winning strategy in this battle was created by Miltiades [[mil-TYE-ah-deez]], who defeated the forces of Darius I. A messenger supposedly ran over twenty miles to report this battle's outcome. For ten points, name this battle of the Greco-Persian Wars that inspired a lengthy footrace.",
      "answer": "Battle ofMarathonor Machē touMarathōnos"
    },
    {
      "question": "Comparing it to the French conquest of Algeria, this act was promoted by Charles Sumner in asenatebill.Inapoliticalcartooncriticizingthisevent,amanmeanttorepresent Andrew Johnson lugs around an iceberg in a wheelbarrow. In an effort to avoid British conquest, Tsar Alexander II sent the diplomat Eduard de Stoeckl [[SHTEH-kul]] to execute this sale. For ten points, name this acquisition of a former Russian colony known to detractors as \"Seward's Folly.\"",
      "answer": [
        "U.S.PurchaseofAlaska",
        "answers whichreferenceBuyingAlaska 2021-22 C Set History"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This nation's partisans like the BOPAassistedintheevacuationofthemajorityofits Jewish population to the neutral Kingdom of Sweden. The United States bought the Virgin Islands from this country, and this European nation gave limited autonomy to its colony of Greenland in 1979. Iceland wasoncecontrolledby,fortenpoints,whatScandinaviannation governed from Copenhagen?",
      "answer": [
        "Kingdom ofDenmarkor KongerigetDanmark",
        "theDanishRealm",
        "or Danmarks Rige"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An injury kept this academic from representing the UK at the 1948 Olympics as a marathon runner. A 2017 \"Law\" named for this scientist provided amnesty to UK men charged under anti-homosexuality legislation.TheBattleoftheAtlanticbegantippinginthe favor of the Allies in large part due to this man cracking the German naval Enigma code. A machine which can replicate any computer algorithm is named for, for ten points, which British computer scientist?",
      "answer": "AlanTuringor Alan MathisonTuring"
    },
    {
      "question": "Future Israeli prime minister Menachem Begin [[meh-NAH-kem BEH-gin]] sent a parcel bomb meant to kill this nation's head of state, instead killing police officer Karl Reichert [[\"RYE\"-kert]]. This state's \"EconomicMiracle\"wasorchestratedbyLudwigErhard [[EHR-hard]] and Chancellor Konrad Adenauer [[AH-den-ow-uh]]. Fortenpoints,namethis country, sometimes known as the \"Bonn Republic,\" which reunified with an eastern communist neighbor in 1990. ANSWER:West Germany(orWest Deutschland; acceptFederal Republic of Germany; or Bundesrepublik Deutschland; acceptFRG; orBRD; donot accept or prompt on \"Deutschland\" or \"Germany\") (8) This politician hired education reformer John Dewey, who suggested switching his country's alphabet to a Latin script. In 1924, this politician formally abolished the last recognized caliph, Abdulmejid II.Followingthisman'sfailuretogettheLeagueofNationsto annul the Treaty of Sèvres [[SEH-vruh]], this head of the Ankara government launched an invasion of the Greek zone of occupation. The father of modern Turkey was, for ten points, which 20th century politician?",
      "answer": [
        "Mustafa KemalAtatürkor Mustafa KemalPasha",
        "Ali Riza ogluMustafa 2021-22 C Set History"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The islandofGotlandinthisseawasthehomeoftheVictual[[VIC-too-all]]Brothers, enemies of the Hanseatic [[HAN-see-at-ik]] League, a trading network of ports around this sea.TheportsofGdańsk[[guh-DANSK]]andStockholmlieonthisbodyofwater,andthecity of Saint Petersburg was created by Peter the Great to ensure Russian accesstothissea.For ten points, name this large sea in northern Europe, namedforanancienttribefromwhatis now Lithuania and Latvia. ANSWER:BalticSea(acceptOstseeand variations; acceptLäänemeri; acceptItämeri) BONUS: A bay of the Baltic Sea is a gulf named for this Latvian capital, which lies on the Daugava [[dow-GAH-vah]] River. It was at one time a leading city of the Hanseatic League. ANSWER:Riga(or Gulf ofRiga; acceptRigo) (2) This general receivedhisnicknameafterservingwiththe10thCavalryoftheBuffalo Soldiers. In one conflict, this man's forces first engaged with the enemy at Cantigny [[kahn-teen-YEE]] and Belleau [[\"BELLOW\"]] Woods. This man commanded the \"dough boys\" during the Meuse-Argonne [[myuhs-ahr-GOHN]]Offensive,aswellasassistingBritish and French forces in the Hundred Days Offensive. For ten points, name this General of the Armies and leader of the American Expeditionary Forces during World War One.",
        "answer": "John \"Black Jack\"Pershingor John Joseph\"Black Jack\"Pershing"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What popular 1917 song proclaimed \"the Yanks are coming!\" and that \"we won't come back till\" World War One was finished?",
        "answer": "\"Over There\""
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's work as a secretary has led to debate over how much of his personal philosophy went intotheFundamentalConstitutionsofCarolina,whichespousedaristocracy and slavery. One work by this thinker outlines the \"State of Nature\" and claimsthatsociety was builttoprotectproperty,whichhedefinedas\"life,liberty,andestate,\"inspiringThomas Jefferson. For ten points, name thisEnglishempiricistand\"FatherofLiberalism\"whowrote Two Treatises of Government.",
        "answer": "JohnLocke"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Much of Locke'sphilosophyisbuiltonthisconcept,establishedinanamesakebook by Jean-Jacques Rousseau. This theory asserts that the public has directly or indirectly consented to give up their personal freedom to an authority in exchangeforprotectionand order. ANSWER:Social ContractTheory (orTheSocial Contract) 2021-22 C Set History (4) A thirty-year clan feud in this state began after Eliza Nichols shot Colonel Charles Jones in the face for maligning her character. Prior to a 1935 assassination, the \"Share our Wealth\" program was touted by this state's governor, known as the Kingfish. In this state, Andrew Jackson's victory over Edward Pakenham[[PAK-en-am]]inan1815battleoccurred months after the Treaty of Ghent ended the War of 1812. The Battle of New Orleans occurred in, for ten points, which southern U.S. state? ANSWER:Louisiana BONUS: The radio program Amos 'n' Andy inspired the nickname \"Kingfish\" for which New Orleans governor? A radical populist, he was assassinated by Dr. Carl Weiss in 1935.",
        "answer": "HueyLongor Huey PierceLongJr."
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Following this event, Enver Hoxha [[HODJ-uh]] pulled Albania out of the Warsaw Pact. In protest of the end of this event, student Jan Palach [[YAHN pah-LAHK]] set himself on fire in Wenceslas [[WEN-seh-slahss]] Square.Militaryinterventionduringthiseventwas justified by the Brezhnev Doctrine. The reforms of Alexander Dubček [[DOOB-chek]]ledto, for ten points, what 1968 period ofliberalizationthatwascrushedbySovietinterventionin the namesake Czech city? ANSWER:Prague Spring(acceptPražské Jaro) BONUS: The events of the Prague Spring mirrored the Soviet suppression of what neighboring country following its Revolution of 1956?",
        "answer": [
          "Republic ofHungaryorMagyarország",
          "acceptHungarianPeople's Republic",
          "or MagyarNépköztársaság 6 During this period, the art of lone storytelling called rakugo grew in popularity as the Chōnin middle class emerged. This period began following a victory by the \"Eastern Army\" over Toyotomi ] loyalists at the Battle of Sekigahara ]. This period's ruling dynasty was weakened when Commodore Matthew Perry forced an end to Sakoku isolation. A clan of Shoguns established by Ieyasu ] ruled from modern-day Tokyo in what historical Japanese period? ANSWER:TokugawaShogunate orTokugawaBakufu",
          "acceptTokugawaPeriod",
          "Jidai",
          "acceptEdoPeriod"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Before moving to Edo, the capital was located in this city in the Kansai [[KAN-\"SIGH\"]] region. This city was made the imperial seat by Emperor Kanmu [[KAN-moo]] in 794. ANSWER:KyotoCity (orKyōto-shi; acceptHeian-kyo;or Kyō noMiyako; orSaikyo) 2021-22 C Set History (7) This man caused a media circus after using \"unparliamentary language\" in front of his fellow politicians in the \"FuddleDuddle\"Incident.Whenaskedwhatmeasureshewould take toendtheOctoberCrisis,thispoliticianrespondedbysaying\"JustWatchMe.\"Thisman invoked the only peacetime use of the War MeasuresActduringaterroristcrisisinQuebec. The father of prime minister Justin was, for ten points,whichCanadianleaderduringmuch of the 1970s? ANSWER:PierreTrudeau(or Joseph PhilippePierreYves ElliottTrudeau) BONUS: Pierre Trudeau was a member of whatcenter-leftCanadianpoliticalparty,laterled by his son, Justin? ANSWER:LiberalParty of Canada (8) Don Pellegrini is executed in this city by a Nazi occupation force led by Major Bergmann in a Rossellini film set in this city, which began his\"Neo-realistTrilogy.\"Ayoung Audrey Hepburn appears as Princess Ann in a 1951 film titled for a \"Holiday\" in this city, visiting sites like the Spanish steps and the Trevi fountain. Ben-Hur's chariot-racing scene occurs in the Colosseum of, for ten points, which Italian capital city? ANSWER:Rome(acceptRome, Open City; acceptRomanHoliday) BONUS: Audrey Hepburn's reporter love interest in Roman Holiday, Joe Bradley, was portrayed by this actor, who played Atticus Finch in ToKillaMockingbirdandstarredinthe World War Two adventureThe Guns of Navarone.",
        "answer": "GregoryPeckor Eldred GregoryPeck"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Second Great Awakening",
      "prompt": "Concerning movements and people involved in the Second Great Awakening, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Calvinist preacher of the period and father of the author ofUncle Tom's Cabin.",
          "answer": "LymanBeecher"
        },
        {
          "question": "Christian sect who celebrates the Sabbath on Saturday, reflected in its name.",
          "answer": "Seventh-DayAdventistorAdventism"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Spanish Civil War",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Spanish Civil War, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Leader of the Nationalist forces that won the war.",
          "answer": "FranciscoFrancoor FranciscoFrancoBahamonde"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Brigade\" named for an U.S. president which supported the Republicans during the war.",
          "answer": "AbrahamLincolnBrigade acceptXV InternationalBrigade"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. author who based his novelFor Whom the BellTollson his experiences in the war.",
          "answer": "ErnestHemingwayor Ernest MillerHemingway"
        },
        {
          "question": "President of Spain and member of the Republican Left Party whose election triggered the war.",
          "answer": "ManuelAzañaor ManuelAzañaDíaz 2021-22 C Set History"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Mali Empire",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Mali Empire, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Mansawho devalued the price of gold in Cairodue to his generosity.",
          "answer": "MansaMusaI"
        },
        {
          "question": "14th century Moroccan traveler who detoured hishajjto spend eight months in the Mali Empire.",
          "answer": "IbnBattuta"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The RogersCommissionwascreatedtoinvestigatethisincident,whichsawthe deaths of Ronald McNair and Francis R. Scobee, among others. Barbara Morgan was (20 pts)",
        "the backup to an intended historical first before thisincident,whichresultedina thirty-two month hiatus for one program.ChristaMcAuliffe,thefaceoftheTeacherin Space Program, died during this Reagan-era (10 pts)",
        "incident. Fortenpoints,namethis1986 disaster in which a Space Shuttle disintegrated 73 seconds after launch."
      ],
      "answer": "Space ShuttleChallengerDisaster acceptdescriptive answers involving the Challengerdisaster"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This president’s Secretary of the Treasury nominee, Caleb Cushing, was rejected by Congress three times in one day. This man's Secretary of State, Abel P. Upshur, and Navy Secretary, Thomas Walker Gilmer, died in an explosion aboard the USS (20 pts)",
        "Princeton. This president opposed Henry Clay’s American System despite running on the Whig ticket. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this president dubbed “His Accidency,” who succeeded William Henry Harrison."
      ],
      "answer": "JohnTyler"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The EcclesiasticalOrdinancesofKingCnut[[CAH-noot]]definedcertainlawsso that these \"madly audacious\" creatures \"do not too widely devastate, nor bite too many of the spiritual flock.\" The geographer Pausanias [[pow-SAY-nee-us]] described how King (20 pts)",
        "Lycaon [[\"lie\"-KAY-on]] became oneofthesecreaturesaftersacrificinga child to Zeus. Modern fiction describes these monstersasbeingvulnerabletoobjects cast from (10 pts)",
        "silver. For ten points, name these historically-feared creaturesthattransform into dangerous canines during the full moon. ANSWER:Werewolf(orLycanthrope; prompt on \"wolf\";prompt on \"shapeshifter\"; accept plurals) (4) Early attempts tosailthisrouteincludedattemptstofindthemythicalStraitof Anián [[ah-nee-AHN]], which was allegedly traversed by Juan de Fuca. Thisroutewas the intended goal of John (+) Cabot's east-west voyage, as well as Jacques Cartier's expedition into the Gulf of Saint Lawrence. Robert McClure was the first to sail this ice-bound (*) route from 1850 to 1854. For ten points, name this sea route between that Atlantic and Pacific Oceans that crosses through the Arctic. ANSWER:Northwest Passage(accept word forms; acceptdescriptive answers before \"Atlantic\") 2021-22 C Set History (5) A ruler of this empire produced the Kandahar [[KAN-dah-har]] Inscription, written in Aramaic and Greek, to encourage foreigners toadopt\"Dharma.\"SeleucusI Nicator [[seh-LOO-kas \"the first\" neh-KAY-tor]] sent the diplomat (+) Megasthenes [[meh-GAS-theh-nees]] to this empire's court, resulting in the ethnography Indika. Much of the Deccan Plateau region was conquered and held by this empire's ruler Bindusara. The Buddhist convert (*) Ashoka ruled, for ten points, what ancient Indian empire founded by Chandragupta [[chahn-drah-GOOP-tah]]? ANSWER:Mauryan Empire (or theMauryans; acceptMuriyaKala) (6) A fake story suggested Ronald Reagan was intended to play the lead in this historical fiction movie. This film was released early to capitalize on free press from Operation (+) Torch, the allied invasion of North Africa. This movie ends with Louis suggesting he join the Free French with Rick Blaine, who states, \"I think this is the beginning of a (*) beautiful friendship.\" For ten points, what Humphrey Bogart andIngrid Bergman Best Picture winner is named for a Moroccan city? ANSWER:Casablanca (7) This man lost a Connecticut congressional run to his cousin and future chairman of the DNC, William Henry. This man purported that a former enslaved person named Joice Heth was, in fact, the 161 year old nurse (+) of George Washington. This man, who unveiled the first aquarium in the U.S., hiredperformers (*) such as the dwarf Tom Thumb andtheoperaticsingerJennyLind.JamesAnthonyBailey paired with, for ten points, which showman to create a namesake 20th century circus?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "P.T.Barnumor Phineas TaylorBarnum",
        "acceptRingling Brothers &Barnum and Bailey Circus"
      ]
    }
  ]
}